Guide to the Cochrane Family Papers, 1777-1957 and undated bulk 1850-1905 RL.00239
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane Series, 1811-1957 bulk 1847-1911, 2 boxes
  - Print Materials Subseries, 1811-1957, 1 folder
    Contents include a pamphlet by William Allman, M.D. on the makeup of vegetables; a prospectus for the London, Hollyhead, and Liverpool Steam Coach and Road Company; an unsigned engagement form for the abolition of the traffic in slaves; a trial report from the case of Gesner v. Halifax Gas Company in 1852; a notification letter of treaty with Russia from 1856; an estate auction form; a printed letter from the royal navy regarding the distribution of prize or salvage monies; a letter patent to Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane for the invention of shields for protection from musketry; copies of two newspapers from Sierra Leone; clippings pertaining to the Cochrane family, including the obituaries for Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane, Lady Francis Higginson, and Thomas Studdert; a racing booklet; a printed volume of poetry by Adelaide Cochrane entitled Sunshine and Shadow; an advertising brochure from the Mineral Asphalte Company; a petition from the Land League and a poem from a Ladies Land League meeting; and several print advertisements. Items are arranged chronologically by date.
    - 1811-1957 and undated (Box 6)
    - Undated, Envelope of calling cards (Box 6)
  - Visual Materials Subseries, 1879, 9 folders
    Folders house nine photographs, and one postcard. Four drawings (one by Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane, the others unsigned) have been removed to Oversize Materials. Items are unsorted.
    - Photograph of the back of Redcastle, undated (Box 6)
    - Small photo card of woman, undated (Box 6)
    - Photograph of three men on a cart, undated (Box 6)
    - Two mounted photographs, one from Peru, undated (Box 6)
    - Photograph of the H.M.S. Peterel, Antelope, and Galatea, undated (Box 6)
    - Photograph of woman, undated (Box 6)
    - Photograph of building with cows, undated (Box 6)
    - Mounted photograph of Redcastle, undated (Box 6)
    - Postcard of Redcastle, undated (Box 6)
- Trinidad Lake Asphalt Series, 1851-1912, 2 boxes
  Contains many folders of documents pertaining to Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane and the Trinidad Lake Asphalt Company, as well as the Union Estate. Divided into the following subseries: Correspondence, Legal and Financial Documents, Notes and Writings, Print Materials, and Visual Materials. Subseries descriptions follow below.
  - Correspondence Subseries, 1851-1912, 1 box
    Subseries contains primarily business correspondence sent to Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane pertaining to the Trinidad Lake Asphalt Company and the Cochrane Pitch Lake properties in Trinidad. Also contains some personal correspondence of Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane, as well as some correspondence written by him to others regarding the properties and business in Trinidad, including one letter copybook from 1865-1866 and a folder containing correspondence and press clippings regarding a "bullet-proof shield" invented by Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane. Arranged chronologically by date.
    - 1851-1912, Correspondence (31 folders) (Box 8)
    - 1865-1866, Copybook (Box 8)
    - 1899 Dec. 23-1900 Jan. 19, Items pertaining to the invention of a bullet-proof shield (Box 8)
    - Undated, Correspondence (Box 8)
  - Legal and Financial Documents Subseries, 1852-1891, 2 folders
    Contents include: letters patent made out to Lord Thomas Cochrane, Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane, and J. Francis Puls regarding innovations in the processing of bitumen and its use in burners and for propulsion; registration forms establishing the Trinidad Bituminous Fuel Company and granting Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane and Henry Mitchell exclusive right in Trinidad to use certain procedures for manufacturing fuel; bills and receipts for the ward of La Brea and Guapo in Trinidad; a prospectus of the West Indian Petroleum Company from 1865; reports concerning tests made of petroleum fuel in steam boilers; assessment rolls of the La Brea and Guapo Ward; incorporation forms for the Hydrocarbon Company; bills pertaining to the purchase of Union Estate in Trinidad and of shares in Trinidad Pitch Lake; a bill of sale of the Mon Plaisir, Belle Vue, and Esperance Estates; a list of payments to be made in the court case of Cochrane v. Dundonald; a Memorandum of Association for the West India Shipping Company; and various financial notes relating to the properties, asphalt and shipping companies, and other financial prospects in Trinidad. Items are arranged chronologically.
    - 1825-1868 (Box 9)
    - 1869-1891 (Box 9)
  - Notes and Writings Subseries, 1861-1904, 4 folders
    Comprises personal notes, business notes, letter drafts, results of experiments, and other miscellaneous writings by Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane pertaining to the Trinidad properties and companies. Also includes one diary by Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane documenting his daily health and activities. Since these papers are mostly for personal or unofficial use, most of them are unsigned and many are undated. Those that are dated are arranged chronologically by date, while the others remain unsorted.
    - 1861-1904 (Box 9)
    - 1889, Diary (Box 9)
    - Undated (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Print Materials Subseries, 1860-1903, 3 folders
    Contains a pamphlet with copies of documents about fitting steam ferry and tug boats as auxiliary gun boats, a page from The Engineer with an entry by James Elliott about Captain Cochrane's advocacy of the testing of bitumen as a cement for sea walls, a report on the uses of bitumen for illumination and cementing sea walls, a regulation sheet for the use and removal of pitch, a copy of the Chilean News (English) from 1871, an advertisement for Harrison's patent gas light improver, clippings pertaining to the Cochrane family and the use of bitumen, and a copy of a supplement to The Financial News from 1899 describing the "Colt automatic quick firing gun." Also included are two bound volumes pertaining to Trinidad. Items are arranged chronologically by date.
    - 1860, 1870-1875, 1903 and undated (Box 9)
    - 1860, Report on the Geology of Trinidad (Box 9)
    - Undated, View Album of Trinidad (Box 9)
  - Visual Materials Subseries, 1851, 1872, 1878, 1 folder
    Subseries comprised of visual materials relevant to the Pitch Lake area in Trinidad. Items are arranged chronologically.
    - 1878 and undated, Maps, plans, drawings, and postcard of the Pitch Lake area, Trinidad (Box 9)
- Oversize Materials, 3 boxes, 3 oversize folders, and 1 oversize tube
  - Family Papers Series, 1860-1925 and undated
    - Legal and Financial Documents Subseries, 1860-1921 and undated
      - 1863-1872, 1880-1883, 1891-1892, 1901-1903, 1908-1921, Rental and account books of Jane Moore Doherty and the Cochranes for the Redcastle, Minitaghs and Rosehill Farm Estates (13 volumes), 13 folders (Box 10)
      - 1860 Aug. 6, 1876 Nov. 12, Naval appointment papers for Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane and Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane (2 sheets) (Box 11)
      - 1870 Jan. 13, Transcript of testimony of James Jonathan Thomas (Box 11)
      - 1885 July 7, Legal brief for the suit brought against Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane by Jane Moore Doherty over the letting of family lands in County Donegal (Box 11)
      - 1896 Nov. 10, Petition for the Clergy Pensions Institution (Box 11)
      - 1914-1918, Rental and account sheets for Ballyloskey Mill Farm (Box 11)
      - Undated, Notice of intent to build railway through the Cochranes' property at Altahalla, 6 folders (Box 11)
    - Print Materials Subseries, 1873-1900
      - 1873, 1882, 1898-1900, Newspaper pages and clippings pertaining to the Cochranes (Box 12)
      - 1882, List of supporters for the Society for Mitigating Disasters at Sea with Harbours of Refuge, 1 folder (Box 12)
    - Visual Materials and Artifacts Subseries, 1868-1876, 1901, 1925, and undated
      - 1868, Unsigned drawing of a cross-section of H.M.S. Recruit (Box 12)
      - 1873, Final notice to tenants from Landed Estates Court of Ireland (Box 12)
      - 1876, Watercolor of Amapala, signed " R. de Lisle" (Box 12)
      - 1901, Plan of a water-powered turbine, unsigned (Box 12)
      - Undated, Sounding chart from Cape Dalou, Borneo, signed " A. Weitch" (Box 12)
      - Undated, Plan of the twin stern with a protected propeller, invented by Alfred B. Sturdee (Box 12)
      - Undated, Plan of an unidentified device, unsigned (Box 12)
      - Undated, Diagram of Tracksel and Clayton's apparatus for burning ozone gas, unsigned (Box 12)
      - Undated, Estate maps of County Donegal by Colonel Sir Henry James, Major General Cameron, and Colonel A.C. Cooke, Directors of the Ordnance Surveys branch of the Landed Estates Court, Ireland (6 maps), 2 folders (Box 12)
      - 1868 and undated, Diagrams of boilers by Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - 1875 Jan. 29, Drawing of coast guard station details (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Undated, Technical drawing of turbine, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - 1925 Nov. 24, Map of Louise Mines ( Bedford County, PA), operated by the Broad Top Fuel Company (Oversize-folder OC:VII:Top, Oversize Tube 1)
  - Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane Series, 1859-circa 1903 and undated
    - Legal and Financial Documents Subseries, 1859-1884
      - 1859 May 14, Appointment of Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane as Deputy Lieutenant of County Donegal (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - 1863 Dec., Notice of application to Parliament by the Dublin Trunk Connection Company to build a railway in County Dublin (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - 1874 Dec. 14, List of Court of Common Pleas costs for Richard Doherty (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - 1880 Sept. 17, Caretaker agreement between Jane Moore Doherty and John Duffy (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - 1884 June 9, Bill of sale of the ship J. Jackson to Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - 1871 Mar. 20, Form certifying Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane Justice of the Peace of County Donegal, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Print Materials Subseries, 1864-circa 1903 and undated
      - 1864 Sept. 15, The Observer and Commercial Advocate, Sierra Leone (Box 12)
      - 1870 Jan. 7, The African Interpreter and Advocate, Sierra Leone (Box 12)
      - Circa 1903, Broadside collecting press articles on electro-peat coal (Box 12)
      - Undated, Printed page listing genealogical information for Thomas Cochrane (Box 12)
      - Undated, Advertisement for W. and F. Thorn, Coach Builders, 1 folder (Box 12)
    - Visual Materials Subseries, 1879 and undated
      - 1879 May 9, Technical drawing of torpedoes by Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Undated, Technical drawing of cross-section of a ship, unsigned (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Undated, Drawing of a paddle ship, titled "Sang's Express Ocean Mail," unsigned (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Undated, Drawing of an unidentified building, unsigned, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Trinidad Lake Asphalt Series, 1851-1899 and undated
    - Print Materials Subseries, 1860, 1899
      - 1860, Map and two geological surveys removed from the volume Report on the Geology of Trinidad (Box 12)
      - 1899 Nov. 13, The Financial News, Industrial Supplement Number 1: Weapons of War and Defense, on the Colt automatic quick firing gun, 1 folder (Box 12)
    - Visual Materials Subseries, 1851, 1865, 1871-1872, and undated
      - 1851, 1865, 1871-1872 and undated, Maps, plans, and diagrams of Pitch Lake and the Cochranes' estate in Trinidad (7 items) (Box 12)
      - Undated, Drawing entitled View of a Portion of the Works, unsigned, 1 folder (Box 12)